All right, so first בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody, today's דף daf
is ל"ג Lamed Gimmel 33 and we pick up at the bottom
of ל"ב עמוד ב' Lamed Bet Amud Bet at the two dots
about four lines before the lines get wide, and we are dealing
again with שבועת העדות, Shevuat Edut, and that the שבועה Shevua even
according to the rabbis that require it to be בבית דין, be-veit
din, it was clarified that the כפירה, kefira, the denial that you
know עדות, edut, has to be בבית דין, be-veit din, otherwise it's
considered irrelevant, it's not a place where the עדות edut is relevant;
but the שבועה shevua itself could have taken place outside of בית
דין, beit din, and then you're חייב chayav for the denial in
בית דין. beit din. Okay, and then we're also dealing with the
fact that it has to be a denial of עדות edut that
is meaningful, so only עדות edut that has the ability to extract
or I guess to protect money, and therefore only שני עדים, shnei
edim, of course. How do you get שני עדים shnei edim and
any person only takes a שבועה shevua one at a time? So
either you have them taking a שבועה shevua simultaneously or within תוך
כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, or the first person who takes the
שבועה shevua is the one that prevents there from being שני עדים,
shnei edim, so he's the one that's חייב; chayav; by the second
guy, you're only up to עד אחד ed echad and therefore he
actually would be פטור, patur, although there was a good debate in
the גמרא, Gemara, there was a position of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rabbi Elazar BeRabbi Shimon that said even an עד אחד ed echad
is חייב, chayav, and there were two ways the גמרא Gemara proposed
thinking about that: one is that an עד אחד ed echad maybe
does obligate money but it could be negated by a שבועה. shevua.
The גמרא Gemara sets that aside and says even if an עד
אחד ed echad only obligates a שבועה, shevua, since it could lead
to money because the person could choose not to take the שבועה,
shevua, its possibility of leading to a payout even though it would
not directly extract the money is enough to make it a weighty
evidence and therefore חייב chayav in a שבועת העדות. shevuat edut. So
that was the position of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar BeRabbi
Shimon, but we're working with the חכמים Chachamim that עד אחד ed
echad is not חייב. chayav. So it would either be שני עדים
shnei edim taking שבועות shevuot together, or the first of the שני
עדים shnei edim that would sort of undermine the weight of the
עדות. edut. Okay, so picking up and continuing with the משנה, Mishna,
bottom of ל"ב עמוד ב' Lamed Bet Amud Bet with the two
dots about four lines before it gets wide: כפר אחד והודה אחד.
kafar echad ve-hoda echad. So it said if they both deny, then
the first one is חייב, chayav, and if one denies and one
admits, the one who denies is חייב, chayav, which is like pretty
obvious. So the גמרא Gemara says השתא בזה אחר זה דתרווייהו קא
כפרי, hashta be-zeh achar zeh de-tarvaihu ka kafri, if it's sequential and
they both are denying, אמרת ראשון חייב והשני פטור, amart rishon chayav
ve-hasheni patur, the first one is חייב chayav and the second one
is פטור, patur, even though the second one also denied, and the
first one could say, hey, even if I hadn't denied, he had
denied, doesn't matter, you denied first so you destroyed the עדות edut
as it were. So if that's true, כפר אחד והודה אחד מיבעיא,
kafar echad ve-hoda echad mibaya, you need to tell me that if
one denies and one admits that the one who denies is חייב
chayav and the one who admits is פטור? patur? I mean, obviously.
לא צריכה, lo tzericha, says the גמרא, Gemara, you need it כגון
שכפרו שניהם, kegon she-kaferu shneihem, they both denied, okay, וחזר אחד מהם
והודה בתוך כדי דיבור. ve-chazar echad me-hem ve-hoda be-toch kedei dibbur. So
this picks up on the תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur discussion
earlier which we discussed was not only a question of the same
time but also the ability to retract. Okay, so therefore they both
denied, Charlie and David, you both deny, and then even let's even
say that Charlie here, let's make it interesting, he was the one
that denied first, so he's the one that would be חייב chayav
in the קרבן, korban, okay, and then David denied after that stage,
David's denial was not yet meaningful because Charlie had already denied. But
then within Charlie's תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, Charlie retracted, so
then David is the one left standing to have the meaningful denial
even though he took the שבועה shevua second.
Okay, דקא משמע לן תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור
דמי, deka mashma lan toch kedei dibbur ke-dibbur dami, it's telling you
that if it's within the time of speech, meaning of like you
know either two or three words, שלום עליך רבי, Shalom Alecha Rabbi,
then it's all as if the same speech act and you can
still retract. So the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא לרב חסדא דמוקי לה
לההיא כרבי יוסי הגלילי רישא אפשר לצמצם וסיפא איצטריך לאשמעונינן תוך כדי
דיבור כדיבור דמי. bishlama le-Rav Chisda de-mokei lah le-hahi ke-Rabbi Yose HaGlili
reisha efshar le-tzamtzem ve-seifa itztarich le-ashmoinan toch kedei dibbur ke-dibbur dami.
So before, when we had two witnesses testifying at the same time,
the גמרא Gemara says how could it really be the same time?
So רב חסדא Rav Chisda said yeah, it's going like רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili who says it's possible for things to happen
at the same time, or הלכתית halachically we define them as happening
at the same time, and yes, that was the case. So according
to that we had not yet introduced the concept of תוך כדי
דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. So the end of the משנה Mishna teaches
you the concept of תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur that even
if one of them, they you know they both denied and one
retracted, the guy who's left standing, the retraction works and the guy
who's left standing is the denier, he's the one that's חייב, chayav,
because the beginning of the משנה Mishna wasn't dealing with that, the
beginning of the משנה Mishna said that they literally did it at
the same time, so then we understand why you need the end
of the משנה. Mishna. אלא לרבי יוחנן, ela le-Rabbi Yochanan, but according
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, he said the beginning, he said you
can't say it happened at the same time, it's impossible to define
things at the same time, so the beginning of the משנה Mishna
that described two witnesses taking the שבועה shevua at the same time
that they're both חייב chayav is, he said that really didn't mean
literally the same time, it meant תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur.
So the beginning of the משנה Mishna was already introducing the idea
of תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, so why do you need
to now introduce it, talk about it again at the end of
the משנה? Mishna? רישא תוך כדי דיבור סיפא תוך כדי דיבור תרתי
למה לי? reisha toch kedei dibbur seifa toch kedei dibbur tarti lamah
li? Why do you need both if both of them are basically
teaching that principle? So again, the סיפא seifa seems redundant. The סיפא
seifa is one denied and one admitted. Of course the one who
denied is going to be חייב. chayav. The only חידוש chiddush we
would say is if the guy who admitted really did initially deny
and then admitted תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. But we've already
introduced that idea. So the גמרא Gemara says no. מהו דתימא הני
מילי כפירה וכפירה, mah d'teima hani mili kfira u'kfira, maybe תוך כדי
דיבור toch kedei dibbur works that, and remember, תוך כדי דיבור toch
kedei dibbur is Charlie finished his testimony and then David began testifying
within a second after Charlie. So maybe that's all seen that Charlie
has the ability to continue retracting as David continues talking, right, remember
we said like daisy chaining? As long as it was within תוך
כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur from the time before the guy before
you ended. So he ended and then within a second you began.
So that's all still considered your continued testimony, David's continued testimony is
all a continuation of Charlie's תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, right?
That's what we said yesterday. Okay, maybe that's only if they're saying
essentially the same thing, okay? But maybe, right, that they're both denying
the testimony, right? So if, right,
person
number one
takes a שבועה shvuah and says שבועה shvuah I don't know, or
he's a כפירה kfira or whatever, maybe without the שבועה, shvuah, I
don't know, etc. And then here, this is תוך כדי דיבור, toch
kedei dibbur, it's one to two seconds, not more. Okay, so this
is person number one, that's whatever his talk bubble.
Okay
and then person number two here, right, within, right, within
one
to two seconds also says שבועה shvuah I don't know. So the
הלכה halakha was that because this is תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei
dibbur, this is all seen as a continuation
of person number one's initial talk, initial speech, since the second one
began within one to two seconds of the first. Okay, so if
this is like a timeline, this is zero seconds, right, and here
he was eight seconds till he finished, and then this began at
nine and here you're all the way here at 12 seconds, even
though it's way out here, this guy can still retract because this
linked with it and since this was within תוך כדי דיבור, toch
kedei dibbur, number one can retract even all the way towards the
end. That was the initial idea, that תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור toch
kedei dibbur kedibbur when they were within one or two seconds and
it even continues after the second guy is talking, it's all considered
still תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. But that's if they're basically
giving the same message. But if this other guy actually says I
do know testimony, right,
so he's saying something different. So in that case, maybe it's not
considered תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur of the first guy, right,
because they're saying different things. So because this is a case of—so
therefore מהו דתימא הני מילי כפירה וכפירה, mah d'teima hani mili kfira
u'kfira, when is it תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור? toch kedei dibbur kedibbur?
When it's denying and denying. Okay, אבל כפירה והודאה, aval kfira vehoda'ah,
but if one guy denies and one guy admits, so אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe it isn't considered like one big talk, קא משמע
לן, kamashma lan, you know, that it is. All right. Now of
course it's a little funny though because our case is not that
he says שבועה shvuah I don't know and he says I do
know, it's that they both started by saying I don't know and
then within this guy's תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, this guy
retracted himself to switch it from I don't know to I do
know. Okay? But anyway, what is still—so that's not as big of
a חידוש chiddush because they initially started saying the same thing and
because they were initially combined and essentially saying the same thing, that
gave him more time to retract. Okay, so that already is not
so much of a חידוש chiddush because at least initially they're saying
the same thing. But anyway, the גמרא Gemara says that yes, it
is the same idea of תוך כדי דיבור, toch kedei dibbur, but
it's telling you that it works even if at the end they
wind up saying different things and not the same thing. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues. היו שתי כיתי עדים כפרו ראשונה
ואחר כך כפרו השנייה. hayu shtei kitei eidin kafru rishona ve'achar kach
kafru hashniya. So now the משנה Mishna says and here actually the
גמרא'ס Gemara's going to interpret the משנה Mishna different than what the
משנה Mishna seems to want to be saying. The משנה Mishna says
you have two groups of witnesses. Okay, if both sets denied it
with a שבועה shvuah in order and let's whatever, let's not worry,
let's assume that each set denied it literally at the same time,
we'll deal with we'll just presume that. Okay? Then both sets are
חייב chayav because each set was a full עדות eidus and they
were denying me the עדות eidus that was relevant to me. So
it sounds like of course the point is when the first set
denied it I still could have used the second set, right, they
were still around, so it sounds like the משנה Mishna is trying
to teach me that if you deny me from a sufficient testimony,
even not a necessary one, you still have withheld a testimony that
could make me win even if I could have gone somewhere else
for the same testimony and you're חייב. chayav. That seems to be
the point of the משנה, Mishna, which is exactly why the משנה
Mishna is saying. even though there are two groups of עדים edim
and each one of them is sort of and it's a little
redundant, nevertheless you denied it to me, you held back a testimony
that could have been that was sufficient for my case and therefore
you're חייב. chayav. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't like this. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. בשלמא שנייה תתחייב, Bishlama shniya
titchayiv,
I understand why the second one is
חייב, chayav, דכפר להו ראשונה, dekfar lehu rishona, because the first one
had already denied it, so it's all resting on the testimony of
the second. אלא ראשונה מאי אמאי, Ela rishona mai amai, why is
the first one חייב? chayav? הכא קיימא שנייה, Haka kayma shniya, top
of ל"ג עמוד א, lamed gimmel amud aleph, the second one is
still around, so even though they denied a testimony, it was not
going to make you lose. It's not a necessary testimony, it's sufficient
but not necessary. אמר רבינא הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהייתה שנייה בשעת
כפירה ראשונה קרובין בנשותיהן. Amar Ravina hacha b'mai askinan kegon she'haita shniya
b'sha'at kfira rishona krovin binshoteihen.
Okay, so here's the case. The case was was that the two
groups could not have testified at the same time. Why could they
not have testified at the same time? It was either A or
B, but it wasn't both because the example was
let's
say the two עדים edim in group A were both were married
the wives
of one of the guys in group A was married to רחל
Rachel and the other guy in group B was married to לאה,
Leah, okay, sisters. And one of the guy any other sisters in
תנ"ך, Tanakh, women sisters? Anyway, one of the guy in group A
was married to I don't know whatever. Anyway,
sister of a different family and the other one was married to
the other sister.
It's assuming two witnesses in the second group were married to sisters
rather than group A and group B. Is that פשט? pshat?
The two witnesses of the sec- oh, I see. So that the
second group was פסול. pasul. Oh, I didn't understand it that way.
Let me look at רש"י. Rashi. קרובין בנשותיהן נשותיהן שתי אחיות ואינם
כשרים בעדות אחת. Krovin binshoteihen nshoteihen shtei achayot ve'einam ksherim b'edut achat.
Oh,
I see. Yeah, that is the way רש"י Rashi reads it. בשלמא
כגון שהייתה שנייה, Bishlama kegon she'haita shniya, oh, I see. Okay.
רש"י Rashi would be the same point.
Yes, I actually see that's a good that's an that's a good
read. Okay. You're right, you're right. Actually, that is more פשט pshat
of what it's saying. Although I think my case is more interesting
than that, but okay.
All right, we'll deal with the גמרא's Gemara case. Whichever it is.
No, 'cause the גמרא's Gemara case is even more obvious. The גמרא's
Gemara case is is that at the time the group one took
the oaths, group two were actually פסול pasul witnesses because the two
witnesses of group two were actually related to one another. But their
wives, who were sisters, were on the deathbed. And therefore, I might
have thought so then it's obvious if group two were פסול pasul
at the time of group one, right, and then their wives died
afterwards and then group two became כשר. kasher. But that's too obvious.
If group two was פסול pasul at the time of group one,
of course group one is חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, the חידוש chiddush is not only they were פסול pasul but
ונשותיהן גוססות, unshoteihen gossot, the wives were on the deathbed, their wives
were the ones that made group two פסול pasul to one another.
מהו דתימא רוב גוססין למיתה, Mahu d'teima rov gosesin l'mita, so I
might have thought to say okay, but since most likely they're going
to die anytime soon, so group two really still is considered theoretically
כשר kasher because that's a principle, רוב. rov. I know. All right,
that's the answer. So I might have thought, okay, I might have
thought that's enough to get group one off the hook because I'm
anticipating that group two is going to be כשר. kasher. So קא
משמע לן השתא מיהא לא שכיב. ka mashma lan hashta miha la
shchiv. Okay, even though it's true that we do say רוב גוססין
למיתה rov gosesin l'mita that they will die soon enough, but they
haven't died yet. Right? Like Monty Python, I'm not dead yet. So
anyway, so therefore right now they're still פסול pasul and therefore group
one is חייב chayav because at this moment I know. So I
would rather have said it, okay, although David is correct that's not
what actually the גמרא Gemara is saying, but I would rather have
said it that group one and group two couldn't testify at the
same time, okay, that they were related to one another not or
within. But of course I think the point would still be that
and but if that were true, here's why the גמרא Gemara didn't
say that 'cause I think it's assuming that if that were true,
group one would still get off the hook. Okay, we can't testify
together with group two but we didn't do anything wrong by by
lying to you. You'll just go to group two. So that's exactly
why your read of that is correct that it means group two
was totally פסול. pasul. But I agree with Michael, it's also pretty
obvious. Not only that, it bothers me that the גמרא Gemara is
just rejecting the פשט pshat of the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah
actually seems to be saying it's enough to be חייב chayav that
your testimony was sufficient. And the גמרא Gemara says you have to
actually be that your testimony was necessary. So if you take a
look, תוספות Tosafot actually says maybe the משנה Mishnah we do go
to say like the משנה, Mishnah, it might depend slightly on the
case. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, הכא קיימא שנייה אמר רבינא,
haka kayma shniya amar Ravina, okay, and then so תוספות Tosafot says,
a minute,
let me find where the answer is, I don't want to bother
you with the question.
You see where it says ויש לומר v'yesh lomar two lines down
in the narrow lines of תוספות. Tosafot. He says, ויש לומר דאף
על גב דכופר במלוה שיש לה עדים, v'yesh lomar d'af al gav
d'kofer b'milveh she'yesh la edim, you denied your witnesses, you denied a
like knowledge of a of a debt and I actually have other
witnesses to that debt, וליתנהו קמן, ve'leitnehu kaman, if those other witnesses
aren't around, they're somewhere in a different state... different town, then סבירא
לן דחייב, svira lan d'chayav, you are חייב. chayav. So what תוספות
Tosfos does is תוספות Tosfos distinguishes between
totally superfluous and theoretically superfluous. Okay, if you are the witnesses that
are right now here in the town in front of me and
yes, there are other witnesses but they're not accessible to me, then
you are חייב chayav because then your testimony is seen as more
necessary, okay, or as immediately the obvious testimony I would go to.
So when does the גמרא Gemara want to be saying that if
it's redundant you're exempt, that's when the other witnesses are immediately present
as well and then since I could just as easily go to
the other witnesses, you're not חייב chayav for your שבועה. shvuah. Okay,
so that's finding some middle ground between the פשט pshat of the
משנה Mishnah which seems to say that it doesn't matter at all
that it's redundant and the גמרא Gemara that seems to say that
if it's redundant you're never חייב. chayav. Okay, and תוספות Tosfos says
maybe it matters how how, you know, easily accessible the other testimony
is. All right, so now we can move to the next משנה.
Mishnah. Top of ל"ג ע"א. Lamed Gimmel Amud Alef. משביע אני עליכם
אם לא תבאו ותעידוני שיש ביד פלוני פלוני. Mashbia ani aleichem im
lo tavo'u v'seiduni she'yesh b'yad ploni ploni. So now we're going to
get to, right until now we've all been assuming the גמרא's Gemara's
been assuming I'd say, that the testimony has to be testimony that's
relevant for monetary issues and actually it is and and has to
be, other than putting רבי אלעזר רבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer Rabbi Shimon
aside who says עד אחד eid echad is enough, it has to
have the power to actually win the case, you know, for the
monetary issues, it has to be two עדים. eidim. So this משנה
Mishnah is now going to sort of lay that out. Now one
of the ways the way it does it and you'll notice it's
about to quote parts of a פסוק pasuk is by comparing שבועת
העדות shvuas ha'eidus to שבועת הפקדון. shvuas ha'pikadon. Okay, so let me
just sort of read you they're both there at the end of
ויקרא. Vayikra. One is a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh v'yored, that's
שבועת העדות. shvuas ha'eidus. שבועת הפקדון shvuas ha'pikadon where you deny having
been given an object for safe keeping is an אשם. asham. Okay,
so the שבועת העדות shvuas ha'eidus is the beginning here of עולה
ויורד, oleh v'yored, פרק ה' פסוק א'. Perek Hei Pasuk Alef. ונפש
כי תחטא ושמעה קול אלה. V'nefesh ki techeta v'shama kol alah. So
you heard the sound of an oath which again is that idea
of like מושבע מפי אחרים, mushba mipi acherim, right, and somebody is
sort of demanding it of you, those ideas we've already seen that
the actual תובע toveia actually is directly making that demand of you.
והוא עד או ראה או ידע אם לוא יגיד ונשא עוונו. V'hu
eid o ra'ah o yada im lo yagid v'nasa avono. And you're
a witness or you've seen or you know, אם לוא יגיד ונשא
עוונו, im lo yagid v'nasa avono, if you don't tell and לא
lo by the way is is is read אם
לוא יגיד, im lo yagid, אם לוא יגיד. im lo yagid. So
just so you know, we discussed this on שבת, Shabbos, we read
this to be אם לא לו יגיד. im lo lo yagid. If
you don't tell us to him. So that that means and from
there we learn that you're only חייב chayav if the actual person
who is demanding your testimony directly makes that demand from you. Okay.
ונשא עוונו. V'nasa avono. Then you bear your sin and it does
not say ונעלם. v'ne'elam. So from there we learn that you don't
have to be a שוגג shogeg even a case of a מזיד.
meizid. However, what's completely absent from that description is what is the
content of the demanding of the עדות, eidus, what is the עדות
eidus about? That's not in that פסוק pasuk at all. So we
learn that from שבועת הפקדון. shvuas ha'pikadon. Okay, and שבועת הפקדון shvuas
ha'pikadon says from the following.
ונפש כי תחטא. V'nefesh ki techeta. This is פסוק כ"ו. Pasuk Chaf
Vav. ומעלה מעל בהשם. U'ma'ala ma'al b'Hashem. So you did a transgression
against God, a trespass. The reason is because you took an oath
about your פקדון, pikadon, so it's a trespass against
God. וכי כחש בעמיתו בפקדון. V'ki kichash ba'amiso b'fikadon. You denied your
friend
an object given for safe keeping. או בתשומת יד. O b'tesumes yad.
Or some type of a, you know, extension of the hand meaning
a misuse of an object. או בגזל. O b'gezel. Something stolen. או
עשק את עמיתו. O ashak es amiso. Or you sort of, you
know, oppressed him. So you sort of, you know, took money that
wasn't deserving to you or you withheld you withheld like his, you
know, his the wages. או מצא אבידה וכחש בה. O matza aveidah
v'kichash bah. Or you found his lost object and you deny it.
ונשבע לשקר. V'nishba l'shaker. And you swear
falsely. So על כל אשר יעשה האדם לחטוא בהנה. al kol asher
ya'aseh ha'adam lachato ba'henah. So all of those are basically denying money.
So we're going to link the two and say that the testimony
by שבועת העדות shvuas ha'eidus that you're חייב chayav for is similar
to the scenarios of the שבועת הפקדון shvuas ha'pikadon where the עדות,
eidus, you're not you're not holding money back that you owe the
guy, you're just holding back testimony, but it's testimony that's relevant to
that type of a monetary issue.
מה כאן דמי הטענה
כסף או שוה כסף אף כאן דמי הטענה כסף או שוה כסף.
Mah kan d'mei
hata'anah
kesef o shoveh kesef af kan d'mei hata'anah kesef o shoveh kesef.
Okay. So we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara. But the משנה, Mishnah,
or as I wanted to read those פסוקים psukim because the משנה
Mishnah is directly going to borrow the language of the פסוקים psukim
of שבועת הפקדון shvuas ha'pikadon and now state it in the context
of שבועת העדות. shvuas ha'eidus. Let's take a look.
What if it's לגבי נפשות? l'gabbei nefashos? Yes.
I mean I don't know if we're going to discuss it but
whatever. Okay. But the answer is it's only by ממון. mamon.
What happens if it's לגבי נפשות?
l'gabbei nefashos? Nothing. You don't get because there's probably like I said,
if it's a capital crime or lashes, so anyway, א', Alef, it's
not included in the פסוק pasuk and ב', Beis, that's not considered
like you have a תובע. toveia. In that case the state is
the תובע. toveia. I understand.
I would agree with that, but the structure here is is that
you are doing a harm to your friend by your you're using
your שבועה shevuah to harm your friend, okay, it's not just that
you're not doing your obligation to God. And when it's a case
involving like lashes or מיתה misah or whatever, the other side is
the state, the other side isn't the aggrieved family. That's what
we only see that in monetary cases.
Now it happened, maybe they would take some measures.
I assume they would, okay, and you probably would be חייב chayav
for שבועת שקר, shevuat sheker, but you wouldn't bring a קרבן. korban.
All right. משביע אני עליכם, mashpi'a ani aleichem, I am imposing an
oath on you, אם לא תבואו ותעידוני, im lo tavo'u ut'iduni, if
you don't testify for me, שיש לי ביד פלוני, she'yesh li b'yad
ploni, that I have in somebody else's hand, somebody else has of
mine, פקדון, pikadon, right, an object for safekeeping, ותשומת יד, v'tesumat yad,
that's something that he like withheld from, like stole from me or
withheld from me, וגזל, v'gezel, stole from me, ואבידה, va'aveidah, directly basically
use the words in the פסוקים psukim by פקדון. pikadon. So you're
trying to get the witness to testify that somebody else owes you
money of some sort. And then they say, שבועה שאין אנו יודעים
לך עדות, shevuah she'ein anu yodim l'cha eidus, we don't know any
testimony. So if they just say a generic we don't know, you
know, אין חייבין אלא אחת, ein chayavin ela achas, so they only
bring one קרבן korban if they're lying.
Even if they denied all three?
Even if they denied all three, but they denied it by just
one שבועה, shevuah, by one by grouping them. Okay, now, שבועה שאין
אנו יודעים שיש לך ביד פלוני פקדון ותשומת יד וגזל ואבידה, shevuah
she'ein anu yodim she'yesh l'cha b'yad ploni pikadon v'tesumat yad v'gezel va'aveidah,
if they identify the objects, and they didn't even say a separate
word שבועה, shevuah, they just identified the objects, so in that case,
חייבין על כל אחת ואחת, chayavin al kol achat v'achat, we treat
it as separate שבועות shevuot and they're חייב chayav for each one
individually. You might remember, we had a similar discussion by שבועת ביטוי,
shevuat bitui, right? I don't know if you remember, where things were
mentioned separately even though it was one word of שבועה shevuah and
they were defined הלכתית halakhically as separate שבועות shevuot for different קרבנות.
korbanot.
Do you mean the things when he said that he doesn't
have your rake, he doesn't have your lawnmower? Right, we're about to
get to that. So these are different categories of ways of types
of ways in which he owes you money. Now we're going to
deal with it's only one type of way he owes you money,
but different objects. Okay. משביע אני עליכם אם לא תבואו ותעידוני שיש
לי ביד פלוני פקדון, mashpi'a ani aleichem im lo tavo'u ut'iduni she'yesh
li b'yad ploni pikadon, that you have to come testify for me
that I have entrusted in him a you know for safekeeping, חטין
ושעורין וכוסמין, chitin use'orin v'kusmin,
wheat and barley and spelt, and that maybe was all done at
the same time, I gave him, you know, three bags at the
same time, it was one category but three objects and I named
the objects. And they say, שבועה שאין אנו יודעים לך עדות, shevuah
she'ein anu yodim l'cha eidus, we don't know any testimony. אין חייבין
אלא אחת, ein chayavin ela achas, that's one one קרבן. korban. שבועה
שאין אנו יודעים לך עדות שיש לך ביד פלוני חטין ושעורין וכוסמין,
shevuah she'ein anu yodim l'cha eidus she'yesh l'cha b'yad ploni chitin use'orin
v'kusmin, if they if they explicitly say you don't have, we don't
know wheat and spelt and barley and they name the objects, חייבין
על כל אחת ואחת, chayavin al kol achat v'achat, then they have
to bring a separate קרבן korban for each one. משביע אני עליכם
אם לא תבואו ותעידוני שיש לי ביד פלוני נזק, mashpi'a ani aleichem
im lo tavo'u ut'iduni she'yesh li b'yad ploni nezek, וחצי נזק. v'chatzi
nezek. נזק. nezek. Now what about if it's different categories and now
we're not going to discuss multiple קרבנות korbanot or one קרבן, korban,
the question is, are you חייב chayav for something that's not straight
it's not a straight ממון mammon payment? It is money, but it's
money in the form of a קנס, knas, of a fine. That's
the basic point of the משנה. mishnah. So נזק nezek for damages,
that's straight ממון, mammon, but חצי נזק, chatzi nezek, half damages, which
is usually when an ox
is a תם tam ox and it gores, that might be considered
more of a fine than of compensation, of a קנס. knas. תשלומי
כפל, tashlumei kefel, paying double for a גנב, ganav, ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה,
v'tashlumei arba'a v'chamisha, four or five if after this גניבה, gneivah, you
know, he slaughtered it or sold it, okay, שאנס איש פלוני את
בתי ופיתה את בתי, she'anas ish ploni et biti u'fitah et biti,
a certain man raped my daughter or seduced my daughter, and there's
a קנס knas of fifty שקל. shekel. So all of those seem
to be קנס knas cases. שהכני בני שחבל בי חבירי, she'hikani bni
she'chaval bi chaveri, or my son hit me or and she and
he wounded me. My son hit me, if he hit me and
it caused was not just הכני, hikani, it was חבל בי בני,
chaval bi bni, he hit me and he drew blood, then he
would be not have to pay because that would then be a
case of חייב מיתה chayav misah and קים ליה. kim lei. But
he actually just said hit without חבלה, chavalah, so therefore it would
be a case where he would have to pay. Or if I
say שחבל בי חבירי והדליק גדישי ביום הכפורים, she'chaval bi chaveri v'hidlik
gdishi b'Yom HaKippurim, my friend wounded me or burnt down my house
or my whatever my haystack on יום הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. So if
he I said he had done that on שבת, Shabbat, he'd be
פטור. patur. Right. But because it's יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, which is
כרת karet and not מיתה, misah, so the author of this תנא
tanna is under the understanding that even by a חייב כרת, chayav
karet, you still have to pay the monetary payment. So all of
these are cases where I might have thought there's no monetary payment
because either I mean, I might have thought it's not straight ממון,
mammon, either because it's קנס, knas, maybe we don't treat קנס knas
as ממון, mammon, or because maybe I would have said קים ליה
kim lei or something of that nature, אבל החידוש הוא, aval hachidush
hu, no, קנס knas is considered ממון mammon and there isn't a
קים ליה kim lei here, so הרי אלו חייבים, harei elu chayavin,
all those cases, it's considered and it's ממון mammon and it is
going to be a קרבן. korban. Let's see the גמרא. gemara. איבעיא
להו, itba'i lehu, they raised the question, משביע עדי קנס מהו? mashpi'a
edei knas mahu? Now that seems to be directly the point of
the משנה. mishnah. But we're going to question whether that was the
message point of the משנה. mishnah. Let's say somebody adjures people who's
who are testifying that this person owes me a קנס, knas, okay,
a קנס, knas, and not compensation, but A קנס. knas. Is that
considered to be testimony that by their denying it they would have
to bring a קרבן? korban? So, אליבא דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון לא
תיבעי לך. aliba de’Rebbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon lo tiba’ei lach. This is
a different רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar bar Rebbi Shimon than
the one we've been dealing with. There's a debate what happens. Everybody
knows the הלכה, halakha, right? That if I admit to a קנס,
knas, I don't have to pay. I can't be held... no self-incrimination
by a קנס, knas, because a קנס knas is a type of
punishment, it's not compensation, so therefore no self-incrimination. But what if I
admit that I owe a קנס, knas, okay, let's say, and then
witnesses come and say I owe? Did my admission get me off
the hook even if witnesses come afterwards? Or does my admission just
mean it's not enough to obligate me? So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rebbi Elazar bar Rebbi Shimon says it just doesn't obligate you, it
doesn't get you off the hook, okay? So he says that therefore
anytime witnesses come they will make you pay, you got it? Even
if it's after my admission. So according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון
Rebbi Elazar bar Rebbi Shimon לא תיבעי לך, lo tiba’ei lach, I
don't have any question. Of course, if they're witnesses to a קנס,
knas, you have to pay, because whenever they come to testify, they
would make the guy pay. So they're real witnesses of money and
therefore they would have... it's a שבועה. shvua. דאמר יבואו עדים ויעידו,
de'amar yavo'u edim v'ya'idu, he says even after you admitted, let the
witnesses come and testify. Witnesses of a קנס knas can always obligate
you. And therefore, if they're denying their testimony, they're holding the money
back from the owner and therefore it's חייב שבועת העדות. chayev shvuat
ha’edut. תיבעי לך, tiba'ei lach, the question is אליבא דרבנן aliba de’rabbanan
according to the Rabbis. דאמרי de'amri who say מודה בקנס ואחר כך
באו עדים פטור. modeh be’knas ve’achar kach ba’u edim patur. After you've
admitted, the witnesses have now been neutralized. They can't testify anymore. So
רבנן Rabbanan now, and therefore the question is, I go to witnesses
and say come and testify for me that Michael was a גנב
gannav and he owes me כפל kefel and whatever, and you deny
it. So you're now going to say, and now I find out
that you guys, you know, and now it's you were lying. Are
you חייב chayev a קרבן? korban? So you can always say look
Dov, we didn't prevent you from collecting from Michael because even had
we been prepared to testify, Michael could have just stepped forward and
admitted it himself. So it's not clear that our testimony really would
have made you win, right? Michael could have just testified. So that
would be the question. Okay, but now one minute, that sounds familiar.
That sounds like something we dealt with yesterday. Your testimony has a
reasonable chance of making me get that money from Michael. It's dependent
on whether Michael beats you to the court or not and admits
it before you. So that's the debate of גורם לממון. gorem le’mamon.
Your testimony won't definitely get that money out of Michael, but it
might depending on whether he admits it or not before you. So
that was a debate of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar bar
Rebbi Shimon and the רבנן, Rabbanan, different debate. Okay, so now so
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Isn't that just tough? Because let's
say the witnesses take two weeks to go, you know? Right, and
they sue them. Well, you know, let's say he doesn't do anything,
right, if you'd have come a little bit earlier. Right, so it's
not just that you hurt me because you were lazy and you
know maybe even you were intentionally lazy, that's true. This is a
קרבן korban for a specific issue, right, you're correct. Okay, so רבנן
דהתם כמאן סבירו ליה? Rabbanan de’hatam k’man seviru leh? Now those רבנן
Rabbanan that say that if the guy admits then the witnesses are
neutralized and you want to know are they חייב chayev a קרבן,
korban, so how does... who are we assuming that they're also holding
like in the other debate of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar
bar Rebbi Shimon and the רבנן? Rabbanan? אילימא ileima if they were
to hold like רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון דהכא Rebbi Elazar bar Rebbi
Shimon de’hacha that we've mentioned here yesterday who holds דגורם לממון כממון
דמי, de’gorem le’mamon ke’mamon dami, so then that you would definitely be
חייב chayev because they lead to a possible loss of money. אלא
כרבנן דהכא ela ke’Rabbanan de’hacha דאמרי גורם לממון לאו כממון דמי, de’amri
gorem le’mamon lav ke’mamon dami, מאי? mai? That going with the Rabbis
that we've quoted yesterday that said the עדים edim are only חייב
chayev if they definitely cause a loss of money, okay, not if
it might cause a loss of money, you know, but if it
definitely... the fact that their testimony would not have definitely made me
win, it's not enough. So that's what the Rabbis said yesterday plus
the Rabbis who said that testimony after the guy admitted you're not...
it's not going to help you. Okay, so then if that's true,
we should say you're not חייב chayev a קרבן. korban. So what's
the question here? Here's the question. Okay, מאי, mai, what do we
say? כיון דאילו מודה מיפטר, keivan de’ilu modeh mifpatar, since were Michael
to admit he'd be exempt, לאו ממונא קכפר ליה, lav mamona k’kafar
leh, you're not holding back money from me, okay, and because you
know you could always say hey look Michael could always just admit
before us and therefore okay we're only גורם לממון, gorem le’mamon, you
know maybe maybe it wouldn't maybe it won't, but the fact that
he could so you can't make us liable, okay? או דילמא odilma
or do we say השתא מיהא לא אודי? hashta miha la odei?
No, it's very different. The cases yesterday were cases where you needed
our testimony plus something else in order to win. You needed us
to testify plus the guy to refuse to make a שבועה, shvua,
right, that was case one, a single עד. ed. Or you need
me to testify plus... the woman to refuse to drink the סוטה
Sotah water. Okay? So the testimony was one piece of a combined
effect that would have made you win. Here, all Michael has to
do for your testimony to make me win is do nothing. Right?
Your testimony alone will make me win provided the status remains quo.
Okay you got the difference? So when do we say that it's
not enough that if it doesn't do it by itself it's not
going to be חייב chayav is when it literally needs something else
to happen. But here what's the story? It doesn't need anything else
to happen for me to win other than that the status remain
quo, that Michael doesn't run to the court and beat you with
an admission. So because maybe we should just define it by the
status quo and say that you're חייב. chayav. Okay? So that's the
question. או דילמא דהשתא מיהא לא אודי, O dilma dehashta miha lo
odi, right now Michael hasn't admitted, so right now your testimony is
going to make me win. תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here.
So now okay so that's the question. Is משביע עדי קנס חייב?
mashpia ede knas chayav? So now we're going to look at our
משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna seems to be quite clear that you're
not. תא שמע, Ta shma, משביע אני עליכם אם לא תבואו ותעידוני
כשיבא פלוני נזק וחצי נזק. mashpiani aleichem im lo tavo vesiduini ksheba
ploni nezek vachatzi nezek. So one of the cases in our משנה
mishna was חצי נזק. chatzi nezek. וחצי נזק קנסא הוא, Vechatzi nezek
knasa hu, but חצי נזק chatzi nezek is a קנס. knas. So
therefore you see that it's חייב chayav and of course the funny
thing is you could say our משנה mishna was ר' אלעזר בר'
שמעון, Rebbe Elazar ber Rebbe Shimon, right we said that our משנה
mishna right our question was only according to a certain lineup of
the תנאים. Tannaim. All right, but we're putting that aside. At least
let's try to show whether how our משנה mishna holds about it.
Okay, so isn't חצי נזק chatzi nezek an example of a קנס
knas and you're חייב? chayav? So the גמרא Gemara says כמאן דאמר
פלגא ניזקא ממונא. Keman damar palga nizka mamona. Ah no, there's an
opinion that says that half, that half payment for a תם tam
ox is considered compensation. הניחא למאן דאמר פלגא ניזקא ממונא, Hanicha leman
damar palga nizka mamona, that's good if you say half compensation half
half נזק nezek is compensation. אלא למאן דאמר קנסא מאי איכא למימר,
Ella leman damar knasa mai ika lemeimar, but what about the opinion
that it's a קנס, knas, according to that opinion is our משנה
mishna clear that you actually you know do do are חייב שבועת
העדות? chayav shvuat haedut? I think I said a long minute ago
because our משנה mishna makes it clear that you're חייב. chayav. Right?
I think I might have misstated that step before. Okay I apologize,
retract that. Go edit the tape. That's right,
it's not so כדי דיבור. kdei dibbur. Well I'm talking השתא, hashta,
the רישא reisha doesn't have השתא. hashta.
Go edit the tape.
Right,
that's actually why our משנה mishna works because our משנה mishna is
actually saying חייב chayav according to all the other possibilities, no forget
that. I don't know, I'm just confusing the situation. Anyway our משנה
mishna makes it clear, seems to make it clear that קנס knas
is חייב. chayav. Okay? So anyway so isn't that
good
evidence? So the גמרא Gemara says no, at least according to the
למאן דאמר leman damar that half קנס, knas, half נזק nezek is
a קנס, knas, isn't our משנה mishna clear that קנס knas is
חייב? chayav? So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא אלא למאן דאמר קנסא
מאי איכא למימר בחצי נזק צרורות. Hanicha ella leman damar knasa mai
ika lemeimar bechatzi nezek tzerorot. Ah, it's a different type of a
half payment, not the half payment of a תם tam ox, but
the half payment of when an animal in walking kicks up stones
and the stones break something. So it's a type of a רגל
regel and it's half because it's not the direct body of the
animal. So even though that normally should have been full, we have
a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha lMoshe mSinai that it's half, but everybody
agrees that that half payment is halachically considered ממון mamon and not
קנס. knas. דהלכתא גמירי לה דממונא הוא. Dehilchata gemiri lah de mamona
hu. All right, so that case in the משנה mishna is not
clear that it's that it's קנס, knas, that might be ממון. mamon.
Okay, but fine, there's a lot of other cases in the משנה
mishna that seem to be קנס. knas. תא
שמע, Ta shma, come in here, תשלומי כפל. tashlumei kefel. So we
have תשלומי כפל tashlumei kefel and you bring a קרבן. korban. That's
קנס. knas. No, משום קרנא. mishum karna. The point, the reason you're
bringing a קרבן korban there is because when I say testify the
guy owes me כפל, kefel, included in כפל kefel is the principal.
Okay, the principal is not קנס, knas, it's only the second payment,
right, the double of it is the קנס, knas, but the principal
is not. So when you witnesses denied to me that Michael was
a גנב gannav and he's חייב כפל, chayav kefel, you're not just
withholding testimony about a קנס, knas, you're also withholding testimony of the
principal. Okay, so maybe אי הכי נמי, in hachinami, maybe if it
was just the קנס knas you'd be פטור. patur.
Okay, תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here,
תשלומי
ארבעה וחמישה, tashlumei arbaa vachamisha, same answer, משום קרנא. mishum karna. I
say Michael stole a sheep and he slaughtered it, come testify four
and five, you're withholding the testimony you're חייב, chayav, but maybe you're
not חייב chayav for the four and five, maybe you're חייב chayav
because implicit in your testimony was also the principal. Okay,
so שאנס פלוני ופיתה בתי, sheanas ploni upitah biti, this certain man
raped or seduced my daughter and there's a payment of the קנס
knas in that case. No, משום בושת ופגם. mishum boshet ufegam. There
are also in those cases are payments of shame and injury and
so on. So yes, those cases are not, maybe the whole חידוש
chiddush of the משנה mishna is not that you're חייב chayav for
קנס, knas, maybe it assumes you're פטור patur for קנס knas and
the חידוש chiddush for the משנה mishna is that you're חייב chayav
because in all those cases there are payments that are not just
קנס knas payments.
בושת ופגם Boshet ufegam is not a קנס? knas?
Right, בושת ופגם boshet ufegam are actually... actual compensations for injury. Okay.
ומאי קא משמע לן כולם ממונא הוא? Umai ka mashma lan kulam
mamona hu? So then what's it teaching me? If that's true, then
the משנה mishnah is just giving me cases of ממון, mamon, why
even bother saying it? It's not a חידוש. chiddush. So רישא חדא
קא משמע לן סיפא חדא קא משמע לן. Reisha chada ka mashma
lan seifa chada ka mashma lan. They're telling me different things. רישא
חדא קא משמע לן דחצי נזק צרורות ממונא הוא. Reisha chada ka
mashma lan dechatzi nezek tzerorot mamona hu. The רישא reisha is telling
me that חצי נזק chatzi nezek is a type of a ממון
mamon and therefore that's why we know it. Well, no, that's first
of all we don't know it already, it's discussed in the גמרא,
Gemara, we don't know it from the משנה. mishnah.
No, from the other משנה. mishnah. No, I don't mean, I mean
other משנה. mishnah.
No, we don't know it from any other משנה, mishnah, it's a
part of a discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. סיפא חדא קא
משמע לן Seifa chada ka mashma lan and the end is teaching
me something having nothing to do with קנס, k'nas, the case of
like a
קים ליה kim leih case. שהדליק את הגדיש ביום הכיפורים Shehidlik et
hagadish beYom HaKippurim to tell me that lighting a, you know, torching
my house on יום כיפור Yom Kippur is חייב chayav because we
don't say קים ליה kim leih even though it's a חייב כרת.
chayav kares. לאפוקי
מאי? Le'afukei mai? What's it excluding?
לאפוקי מדרבי נחוניא בן הקנה. Le'afukei mi-deRabbi Nechunya ben HaKanah. דתניא Detanya
Rabbi Nechunya בן הקנה ben HaKanah היה יום הכיפורים כשבת לתשלומים. haya
Yom HaKippurim keshabbat letashlumim. Okay, Rabbi Nechunya ben HaKanah says that the
same way if you did it on שבת Shabbat you'd be פטור
patur because of קים ליה, kim leih, if you do it on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, מה שבת mah Shabbat you're פטור, patur, even
יום כיפור Yom Kippur you're פטור. patur. So our משנה mishnah is
rejecting that. So the end of the משנה mishnah we know is
not about קנס. k'nas. The end of the משנה mishnah is telling
me you don't say קים ליה kim leih on a יום כיפור
Yom Kippur case. But the beginning of the משנה mishnah seems to
be about קנס k'nas and being מחדש mechadesh that קנס k'nas you're
going to be חייב. chayav. But the גמרא Gemara is saying maybe
its point is really to tell me that some of those cases
aren't קנס, k'nas, that the case of חצי נזק chatzi nezek is
a ממון mamon case. So the way I said it, maybe part
of the חידוש chiddush is that even though there's a קנס k'nas
element to those cases and that might even be your focus, since
the denial also includes a denial of principle, then therefore that's why
they're going to be חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says you
can't prove it from the משנה. mishnah. Of course, as I said
before, big deal. Let's say the משנה mishnah does say you're חייב
chayav for קנס. k'nas. Maybe the משנה mishnah is going like רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon that says you're חייב chayav
for דבר הגורם לממון davar hagorem lemamon or it's going like the
other רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon that says you're
חייב chayav that even in a case of קנס k'nas if the
witnesses come even after the admission it's חייב. chayav. So even if
the משנה mishnah were saying you're חייב chayav in קנס, k'nas, it
doesn't prove what the הלכה halacha would be according to the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Okay. But anyway the גמרא Gemara raises that question, according to
the רבנן Rabbanan that say number one, we don't say דבר הגורם
לממון davar hagorem lemamon and number two, if the guy beat them
to the בית דין Beit Din with an admission he'd be off
the hook, do we say in that case they're חייב? chayav? Right
now their testimony will make me win if the status remains quo,
but if the guy beats them to בית דין Beit Din it
won't. Would that be enough to be חייב? chayav? And we're saying
we don't know the answer. Wait a second.
Is it true דבר
הגורם לממון davar hagorem lemamon does not make you חייב? chayav? I
mean if I borrowed a hundred dollars or Coca-Cola, okay, then the
witnesses say, 'Oh, well, you know, we don't know anything,' then they
get you out of it, then you can go after the witnesses
because they're... you know what I mean, you've recourse only against them
monetarily. All you have to do is bring a קרבן, korban, right?
The witnesses are not חייב chayav money.
No, the point is דבר הגורם לממון davar hagorem lemamon is not...
well no, דבר הגורם לממון כממון דמי davar hagorem lemamon kemamon dami
is not just a question of נזק. nezek. דבר הגורם לממון davar
hagorem lemamon is also a question of do we consider that the
testimony was about ממון mamon or not, was about like the חפצא,
cheftza, it's not just is it considered damages. Okay, it's like it's
also a question about פסח. pesach. If I own something that the
loss of it will make me compensate, is it like it's my
חמץ chametz that I'm חייב לבער? chayav leva'er? It's not just a
נזק nezek question. תא שמע: Ta shema: משביעני עליכם ולא באתם והעדתוני
שהוציא פלוני שם רע על בתי. Mashbi'ani aleichem velo batem ve'idatuni shehotzi
ploni shem ra al biti. Here's a ברייתא. braita. Come and testify
to me that a certain person spread a false report about my
daughter, and in that case if it's proven that he did so
he has to pay the father a קנס, k'nas, okay, and that's
a pure
קנס. k'nas.
חייבים. Chayavim. So in that case and they denied it, they're חייב.
chayav. הודה מפי עצמו, Hoda mipi atzmo, but if the guy went
ahead and beat them to בית דין Beit Din and admitted, פטור,
patur, then they'd be exempt. So that seems to me saying exactly
that point, that even though it's true that if he beats them
to בית דין Beit Din that the guy will get out of
paying and if that happens first and then they're withholding their testimony
they are exempt because at that stage it's already been
neutralized, right, if they deny it before he admitted in בית דין
Beit Din it sounds like they're חייב. chayav. That sounds like exactly
our case. So the גמרא Gemara says הא מני רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון היא דאמר יבואו עדים ויעידו. Ha mani Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon
hi de'amar yavo'u edim veya'idu. Yeah, fine, you've proven it, but this
is what I was saying about the משנה. mishnah. Anytime you prove
that you're חייב chayav for קנס k'nas I'll just say it's רבי
אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon. Fine, that was רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon that would say even after he
admitted the עדים edim could come and testify, so of course they're
going to be חייב chayav all the time. So the גמרא Gemara
says one minute, אימא סיפא הודה מעצמו פטור. eima seifa hoda me'atzmo
patur. But wait a minute, doesn't sound like that, because the end
sounds like if the guy admits he's פטור patur and presumably it
means he remains exempt even if the עדים edim come afterwards. אתיא
לרבנן. Atya leRabbanan. That sounds like it's going like the רבנן, Rabbanan,
that even after the admission he's exempt. No, כולה רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון היא. kulla Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon hi. No, no, it's all
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon. והכי קאמר: Vehachi ka'amar:
לא משכחת להודה מפי עצמו דפטור אלא היכא דליכא עדים כלל והודה
מעצמו. Lo mashkachat lehoda mipi atzmo depatur ela heicha delika edim klal
vehoda me'atzmo. No,
the whole point of the ברייתא braita would be saying, 'You know
why the witnesses are חייב chayav when they deny the testimony? Because
the only time the guy is exempt is if he comes in
and admits it when there are no witnesses at all.' admits and
there are no witnesses. If he, but the witnesses never show up.
But since as long as the witnesses show up even after he
admits he'd be חייב, chayav, that's why they're חייב chayav when they
deny. So it's probably not פשט pshat of the ברייתא beraisa which
the גמרא Gemara acknowledges, but the גמרא's Gemara saying maybe the point
of the ברייתא beraisa is they're חייב chayav because the guy's admission
never fully gets him off the hook. But the simple sense of
the ברייתא beraisa is exactly what the גמרא Gemara was looking for.
Even though the guy's admission would get him off the hook, if
the witnesses denied before the guy had a chance to admit, the
witnesses are חייב, chayav, anyway that seems to be the question we
were asking. Next משנה. mishna. משביע אני עליכם אם לא תבואו ותעידוני
Mashbi'a ani aleichem im lo tavo'u veta'iduni now. Now we're going to
get to the point that it has to be testimony that is
about monetary issues. Okay, I'm... I've imposed an oath on you that
you have to come testify for me שאני כהן, she'ani kohein, שאני
לוי. she'ani levi. Okay, people are questioning my status. Okay, I need
you to come testify for me that I am a כהן kohein
or I'm a לוי, levi, שאיני בן גרושה ושאיני בן חלוצה. she'eini
ben grusha veshe'eini ben chaluza.
Interesting, this only has relevance to the time of the בית המקדש?
Beis Hamikdash?
Yeah, that's true. I mean well מעשר, ma'aser, I mean they were
still giving מעשר ma'aser
even post בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. They were even giving תרומה truma
to the לוי levi after תקנת עזרא, takanas Ezra, okay at least
דרבנן. derabanan. Okay anyway, okay, or people are questioning my כהן kohein
status because they're claiming that my mother was a גרושה grusha or
חלוצה, chaluza, I need you to testify otherwise. Okay, so here's a
case where and again this is different than the מלקות malkos and
the מיתה misa because the מלקות malkos and the מיתה misa like
I said is not really a case where there's a other side,
the state is the other side. Here there's a case that actually
is testimony about me. I am a תובע, tovei'a, I need your
I personally need your testimony but not in a monetary matter, in
a status matter. One minute.
Okay. שאיש פלוני כהן. she'ish ploni kohein. Now this is an easier
case because as we've already learned in the... the person who needs
the testimony has to be the one demanding it. So this is...
this is like a trivial case, this case. Come and testify that
that person over there is a
כהן, kohein, שאיש פלוני לוי, she'ish ploni levi, שאינו בן גרושה ושאינו
בן חלוצה, she'eino ben grusha she'eino ben chaluza, he's not a son
of a גרושה grusha or חלוצה. chaluza. Okay, so that's pretty obvious.
שאנס איש פלוני את בתו ופתה את בתו. She'anas ish ploni es
bito upita es bito. Or come testify that that person there, you
know, raped, that ראובן Reuven raped שמעון's Shimon daughter.
Okay, Reuven, what power do you have?
You don't. So the end of these cases are obvious. Okay, so
if you are going to say if it was that raped my
daughter, that was the previous משנה, mishna, they're חייב. chayav. So the
end of this משנה, mishna, although you know it should have said
an easier case: come testify that ראובן Reuven borrowed a hundred dollars
from שמעון. Shimon. It's funny because the הלכה halacha is is that
you need the guy to whom it relates to, the תובע tovei'a
demand it himself. So it's a little funny that it gives the
examples that you're פטור patur of of less standard cases. Testify that
that guy is a כהן. kohein. Testify that ראובן Reuven raped שמעון's
Shimon daughter. Okay, ושחבל, veshechaval, okay,
ושחבל בי בני veshechaval bi beni or my son wounded me. So
again that's not ממון mamon because that would be קים ליה. kimlei.
Okay, this is a little bit parallel of the, you know, the
mirror image of the previous משנה. mishna. ושחבל בי חברי ושהצית גדישי
בשבת veshechaval bi chavera veshehitzit gadishi beshabos or testify that that guy
burned down my house on שבת Shabbos or wounded me on שבת.
Shabbos. In all those cases he's פטור patur because of קים ליה.
kimlei.
Okay, ושחבל בי חברי veshechaval bi chavera is on שבת?
Shabbos? Yeah. הרי אלו פטורים. Harei elu paturim. So the end is
פשוט pashut because of קים ליה. kimlei. Okay, and the middle cases
are פטור patur because it's not about me, it's about somebody else.
והחידוש, vehehiddush, the bigger חידוש chiddush is the first cases that it
does it have to be about monetary issues and not status issues.
Yes, Charlie?
But there are monetary issues involved. If I'm not a priest I
can't get תרומה. truma.
Right, but that's not a direct mon... that's not direct. And since
it's not direct, that's not considered, that's correct, I could lose that
money by not being a priest but that's not direct. Okay, I
mean I don't know, let's say say come and testify to me,
hey, you know, they want to fire me from my job because
they think I stole from the, you know, from the supply cabinet,
you know, come and testify for me that I didn't and you're
not going to testify and I'm going to get fired, okay, but
it seems like since it's not a direct issue of money, even
though it has monetary consequences, although it's interesting to ask according to
רב אלעזר בר שמעון Reb Elozor bar Shimon that דבר הגורם לממון
davar goreim lemamon
might maybe that would be relevant to some of those cases. Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. טעמא דאיש פלוני
כהן דאיש פלוני לוי. Ta'ama de'ish ploni kohein de'ish ploni levi. So
the גמרא Gemara picks up that the משנה mishna when it talks
about testify for another person it use these not standard cases, testify
about ראובן Reuven that he's a כהן kohein or לוי. levi. המנה
לפלוני ביד פלוני Hamaneh leploni beyad ploni it sounds like if it
was a standard case testify that ראובן Reuven owes שמעון Shimon a
hundred dollars, חייבין chayavin it sounds like that you would be חייב.
chayav. But we know that that's not true, you need to make
the demand yourself. התני סיפא, Hatni seifa, but a later משנה mishna
is going to say explicitly עד שישמעו מפי התובע, ad sheyishma mipi
hatovei'a, they actually have to have the demand of the testimony made
by direct... directly by the person to whom it relates.
So אמר שמואל amar Shmuel בבבא דהרשאה. bevava deharsha. Okay, the חידוש
chiddush here is you're right. Our case in the משנה mishna is
that the guy is coming with a power of attorney. Okay, so
if Michael goes and I've given Michael my power of attorney and
he makes Charlie and David take an oath. I demand that you
come and testify for Dov in a court case that he's given
me power of attorney and you take an oath, you're חייב. chayav.
Because he has my power of attorney, he becomes my representative and
my תובע. tove'a. Okay, not just he's doing me a favor or
an agent, he explicitly has my power of attorney. He can actually
bring the other person to court, so he becomes like me and
therefore you're חייב. chayav. But let's say I give him my power
of attorney about this case about whether I'm a כהן Kohen and
he goes and he makes that demand about you. You're not חייב
chayav because there is really no meaningful power of attorney by a
כהן. Kohen. The way power of attorney works in הלכה halacha is
that effectively I transfer the money, okay, I claim that ראובן Reuven
owes me a hundred dollars. You guys know the testimony and I
want Michael to be my power of attorney. So the way I
make him my power of attorney is I say Michael, that hundred
dollars that ראובן Reuven owes me, it'll be like I'm transferring that
money to you. It's sort of like a combination of שליחות shlichus
and הקנאה. hakna'ah. It's a little bit of a legal fiction or
a lot of legal fiction. But part of the legal fiction requires
that we look at it as I've given Michael the hundred dollars
that ראובן Reuven owes me. And therefore he can sue ראובן Reuven
on my stead and he can demand from you witnesses on my
stead. But if the question is if I'm a כהן, Kohen, I
can't make Michael me, who has the same status issues as me
to represent me. So therefore the הרשאה harsha'ah doesn't work, and that's
why when he comes to you guys, it's not going to be
like I'm demanding it, okay? So that's what שמואל Shmuel says. You're
right. If it was סתם stam a person demanding testify that ראובן
Reuven owes שמעון, Shimon, then they would not be חייב chayav because
you're not demanding it for yourself. The חידוש chiddush of our משנה
mishna that it's about somebody else and you're פטור patur and it's
a כהן Kohen case is even with the power of attorney which
would work if it was a monetary issue, does not work in
this case of a כהן Kohen case. בבא בהרשאה. Beva beharsha'ah. So
the גמרא Gemara says והאמרי נהרדעי לא כתבינן אורכתא אמטלטלי. veha'amri Nehardai
lo katvinan urchata amitaltalei. One minute, but doesn't נהרדעי Nehardai say that
you don't write a הרשאה harsha'ah on chattel? So therefore if it
was a case of ראובן Reuven owes שמעון Shimon a hundred dollars,
okay, and presumably we're not talking about land because there's a whole
question if this rule applies by
land. Presumably so you're saying that if it were about a hundred
dollars Michael would be able to make that demand of you. But
wait, הרשאה harsha'ah doesn't work if it's about chattel, not about land.
And the reason for that is again, what's the logic? If I
have to effectively give Michael the hundred dollars that ראובן Reuven owes
me, if it's just something that's movable and chattel or whatever, how
can I pretend like I'm giving it to him? Who knows where
that hundred dollars is, right? But if it's a plot of land,
then I can say yes, ראובן Reuven is on my land, but
it's right there, I see it, it's mine, it's easier for me
for us to hold the fiction that I've transferred that land to
Michael than that I've transferred abstract funds to Michael. Do people get
this? Yes? Okay. So therefore how can you say this הרשאה harsha'ah
works by a monetary issue? We say that הרשאה harsha'ah doesn't work
if it's only chattel. If it's only, so the גמרא Gemara says
הני מילי היכא דכפר. hani milei heicha dekafar. Yes, after ראובן Reuven
has denied that he owes me the money, then I can't give
that money to Michael if it's not land, because then it's like
I don't have access to that money at all. אבל לא כפר
כתבינן. Aval lo kafar katvinan.
If ראובן Reuven has yet to deny it, I haven't brought ראובן
Reuven to court yet, he hasn't yet made a public denial of
it, then I can give still Michael the power of attorney and
then Michael can make the demand from the witnesses on my behalf.
So that's how it works in a monetary case, but it would
not work that way in a status case and in a כהן
Kohen case, okay? By the way, as a matter of practical הלכה,
halacha, if you look three lines from the bottom here of the
תוספות Tosafot right before the תוספות Tosafot lines get wide, it says
רבינו תם פוסק דכתבינן אפילו אמטלטלי דכפר. Rabbeinu Tam posek dekatvinan afilu
amitaltalei dekafar. That we do write a הרשאה, harsha'ah, this just because
again as people know in the Middle Ages right, it was less
agricultural more commercial, there needed to be a general expansion of some
of these devices. So רבינו Rabbeinu says we do write it on
those types of מטלטלין metaltelin even after they've been denied because he
says דטעמא דלא כתבינן deta'ama delo katvinan the only reason we don't
write it is מפרשי משום דמיחזי כשקרא. mifarshei mishum dimechezi keshikra. Because
it like, it looks like a farce, okay? That I how can
I say I'm giving Michael the money ראובן Reuven owes me if
ראובן's Reuven already denied it? But then רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says
we don't really worry so much about things looking like a farce,
okay? Yes, a fiction anyway, we don't worry about that and you
can do it. So that's interesting that's the halachic change. Back to
the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tano rabanan. Okay, מניין שאין הקרבן מדבר
אלא בתביעת ממון? minayin she'en hakorban medaber ela bitvi'at mamon? So that
was the issue about if it's a third party. Generally you need
the person directly. Our משנה mishna is talking even with a case
of a power of attorney, it doesn't work in a status issue
if it's about somebody else. But the basic point of our משנה
mishna was it needs to be a money issue, it can't be
a status issue even if it directly affects me. I need testimony
that I'm a כהן. Kohen. So how do you know this? מניין
שאין הקרבן מדבר אלא בתביעת ממון? minayin she'en hakorban medaber ela bitvi'at
mamon? רבי אליעזר אומר. Rabbi Eliezer omer. נאמר כאן אוים ונאמר להלן
אוים. Ne'emar kan oin v'ne'emar lehalan oin. I love this. Okay, it
says the word או o multiple times. It says והוא עד או
ראה או ידע. vehu ed o ra'ah o yada. It says a
lot of or this or that. Okay, and it says by שבועת
פיקדון, Shevuat Pikadon, right, it says או בתשומת יד או בגזל או
עשק את עמיתו, o b'tsumet yad o b'gazel o ashaq et amito,
או או או או, o o o o, or or or or.
So the אוים, oin, the multiple או'ס, o's, link the two. And
the same way שבועת פיקדון Shevuat Pikadon is about monetary issues, שבועת
העדות Shevuat Ha'edut is about monetary issues. Okay. ונאמר להלן אוים מה
להלן אינו מדבר אלא בתביעת ממון, v'ne'emar lehalan oin mah lehalan eino
medaber ela bitviat mamon, it's about monetary, אף כאן אינו מדבר אלא
בתביעת ממון. af kan eino medaber ela bitviat mamon. So the גמרא
Gemara says אוים דרוצח יוכיחו, oin de'rotzeach yochichu, what do you mean?
It also says אוים oin by the case of murder. What does
it say by murder? So it says
או באיבה הכהו או השליך עליו בצדיה, o b'eivah hikahu o hishlich
alav bitzdiya, he killed him with enmity or he killed him, he
was lying in wait. So it says a lot of או o
or or or there. שאין אוים ומדברים שלא בתביעת ממון, she'ein oin
u'medabrim shelo bitviat mamon, and that's not about money. And here maybe
the גמרא Gemara is thinking about the question raised before. Maybe therefore
שבועת העדות Shevuat Ha'edut would be relevant to a murder case? Okay.
No. דנים אוים שיש עמהם שבועה מאוים שיש עמהם שבועה. danim oin
sheyesh imahem shevuah me'oin sheyesh imahem shevuah. Our two cases about שבועת
העדות Shevuat Ha'edut and שבועת פיקדון, Shevuat Pikadon, first of all they're
right next to each other in the תורה Torah and they're both
talking about a שבועה. shevuah. So we're going to learn one from
the other. We're not going to go to a רוצח rotzeach case
which is completely irrelevant. ואל יוכיחו אוים דרוצח, v'al yochichu oin de'rotzeach,
don't try to prove to me from the אוים oin of a
murder case, שאין עמהם שבועה, she'ein imahem shevuah, which is not in
the context of a שבועה. shevuah. Okay. אוים דסוטה יוכיחו. oin de'sotah
yochichu. How about the אוים oin by סוטה, sotah, right? It says
what does it say by סוטה? sotah? או עבר עליו רוח קנאה
וקינא את אשתו או עבר עליו רוח קנאה והיא לא נטמאה. o
avar alav ruach kinah vekinah et ishto o avar alav ruach kinah
v'hi lo nitma'ah. Or this or that. And by a סוטה sotah
an oath is imposed on her and it's about something that she
did wrong but it's not about monetary
issues. Okay. שאין אוים ויש עמהם שבועה ומדברים שלא בתביעת ממון, she'ein
oin veyesh imahem shevuah u'medabrim shelo bitviat mamon, not about monetary issues.
So maybe we should learn from there that it doesn't have to
be monetary. No. דנים אוים שיש עמהם שבועה ואין עמהם כהן. danim
oin sheyesh imahem shevuah ve'ein imahem kohen. No, no, no. Because סוטה
sotah is distinct, it has an oath but an oath that's done
through a כהן. kohen. Okay. So we'd rather learn שבועה shevuah cases
without a כהן kohen rather than from a שבועה shevuah case with
a כהן. kohen. מאוים שיש עמהם שבועה ואין עמהם כהן. me'oin sheyesh
imahem shevuah ve'ein imahem kohen. So you learn the two similar שבועה
shevuah cases without a כהן. kohen. ואל יוכיחו אוים דרוצח v'al yochichu
oin de'rotzeach and we won't learn it from the case of murder
שאין עמהם שבועה she'ein imahem shevuah that isn't dealing with an oath
at all. ואל יוכיחו אוים דסוטה v'al yochichu oin de'sotah and don't
learn it from סוטה sotah שאף על פי שיש עמהם שבועה יש
עמהם כהן, she'af al pi sheyesh imahem shevuah yesh imahem kohen, although
there is a שבועה shevuah there also is a כהן. kohen. So
that's one from the או או o o is how we learn
it out. רבי עקיבא אומר והיה כי יאשם לאחת מאלה. Rabbi Akiva
omer v'hayah ki yesham l'achat m'eleh. It says at the end, it
says if he sins from any one of these, it says by
the case of the
שבועת העדות, Shevuat Ha'edut, okay, it also שבועת העדות Shevuat Ha'edut and
by the טומאת מקדש, tum'at mikdash, all the cases of what do
you call it? And the שבועת ביטוי, shevuat bitui, all the cases
of קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh v'yored. So he says יש מאלה
שהוא חייב, yesh me'eleh shehu chayav, מאחת מאלה, m'achat me'eleh, from some
of these types of situations you'll be חייב. chayav. ויש מאלה שהוא
פטור, v'yesh me'eleh shehu patur, in some situation like this you'd be
exempt. כיצד הטענת ממון חייב דבר אחר פטור. keitzad hat'anat mamon chayav
davar acher patur. If you demand the money you're חייב, chayav, something
else you're exempt. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva doesn't really know from
the פסוק pasuk clearly that it's about monetary issues. He says the
פסוק pasuk tells me you're not חייב chayav in every case of
testimony. Some you're חייב, chayav, some you're פטור. patur. I'm going to
decide to draw the line between if it's a monetary issue or
not a monetary issue. So the גמרא Gemara is going to ask
how do you know according to that that's where you draw the
line? Maybe you draw the line somewhere else. Okay, so he doesn't
directly learn monetary, he just learns you're not חייב chayav in all
cases and I'm going to decide that means monetary versus non-monetary.
One more דרשה, drashah, רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר הרי הוא אומר והוא
עד או ראה או ידע. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer harei hu omer
vehu ed o ra'ah o yada. He knows or he
saw. עדות המתקיימת בראיה בלא ידיעה, edut hamitkayemet b're'iah belo yedi'ah, it's
a type of a testimony that it's possible to see it without
knowing the specifics and it would be relevant testimony, או בידיעה בלא
ראיה, o b'yedi'ah belo re'iah, or knowing it without actually having witnessed
it. במה הכתוב מדבר? bameh hakatuv medaber? And those things only occur
in monetary cases. How can you get those in monetary cases? ראיה
בלא ידיעה כיצד? re'iah belo yedi'ah keitzad? What's seeing something without knowing?
כיצד? keitzad? I go and I say to Charlie and Dave over
there, מנה מניתי לך בפני פלוני ופלוני, maneh maniti lach bifnei ploni
u'ploni, you saw me count out a hundred dollars and hand it
over to Michael. Okay, now you don't know was that I was
paying him back a debt, I was giving him a gift, I
think I'm saying it's a loan. You guys don't know the context
but I'm saying I need you to come to court to testify
because once you testify to that in court Michael will admit that
it was a loan. So I need that testimony. Okay. יבוא פלוני
ופלוני ויעידו, yavo ploni u'ploni v'ya'idu, come and testify. זו היא ראיה
בלא ידיעה, zu hi re'iah belo yedi'ah, that's seeing something without knowing
what it means. That can happen in monetary cases but presumably it
can't happen in like what do you call it? In like a
capital crime. If I say, you know, I don't know what, like
I saw you, you saw somebody doing something and I don't know
if what he was doing was he was, you know, he did,
he turned on a machine. He made a fire on שבת, Shabbat,
but it might be because he was helping a, he was a
doctor, and he might have been helping a patient, or it might
be that he was מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat, I really don't know.
So that testimony is irrelevant if you don't know what it means.
Okay, because the court objectively needs to determine, but here it is
relevant because your testimony that I gave Michael a hundred dollars could
pressure Michael into admitting why he did. Of course that sounds like
גרמא לממון Garma Lemamon and רב אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar Berabbi
Shimon because it still requires Michael's admission. Anyway, ידיעה בלא ראייה, Yedi'ah
belo re'iyah, now this is a better example, knowing without
seeing. Okay, כיצד? Keitzad? מנה הודית לי בפני פלוני ופלוני. Maneh hodita
li bifnei ploni uploni. I say, Michael, you admitted to me that
you owed me a hundred dollars, and you admitted in front of
Charlie and David there. יבוא פלוני ופלוני ויעידו, Yavo ploni uploni ve-ya'idu,
let them testify. So they don't know that I really lent you
the hundred dollars, they just know that you admitted it. So they
know about it without having seen it. זו היא ידיעה בלא ראייה.
Zo hi yedi'ah belo re'iyah. And those he says occurs only in
monetary cases. If you know that somebody was מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat
without having directly witnessed it, then that's not acceptable in court. But
it is acceptable, at least a form of that, when it's a
monetary issue. So that's how he knows that it's monetary. Okay, last
one for what we'll do for today. רב שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon
Omer. Yes?
In case you just gave an example about seeing somebody make a
fire and not being sure,
so can't you testify you saw he made the fire and then
the person has to explain why he— No, he doesn't have to
explain. Unless the court can prove that he was מחלל שבת. mechallel
Shabbat. I mean, it's an interesting point. If there's a חזקה, chazakah,
you're right, like, yes. I mean, that's why I said he was
a doctor and maybe it was for this reason. Right, right. Yes,
there are cases where by default we would assume certain things unless
you could prove otherwise. There are other cases which from the very
outset we don't know what they mean. Okay, so that was the
type of scenario I was giving. רב שמעון אומר חייב כאן וחייב
בפיקדון. Rabbi Shimon omer: chayav kan ve-chayav be-fikadon. So he seems to
say like the או או o o drasha, we're just going to
make a comparison to the פיקדון fikadon case. You're חייב chayav by
this, you're חייב chayav by the פיקדון. fikadon. מה להלן אינו מדבר
אלא בתביעת ממון, Ma le-halan eino medaber ela bi-tvi'at mamon, the same
way פיקדון fikadon is monetary, אף כאן אינו מדבר אלא בתביעת ממון.
af kan eino medaber ela bi-tvi'at mamon. Here too, it's only monetary.
ועוד קל וחומר. Ve-od kal va-chomer. And it's a קל וחומר. kal
va-chomer. So the first one we don't even know, it's just like
some analogy, it's like the או או o o thing, except weaker.
But I'll make you a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. מה פיקדון שעשה
בו נשים כאנשים, Ma fikadon she-asah bo nashim ke-anashim, פיקדון fikadon is
broader cases, you're חייב, chayav, men and women you're חייב, chayav, קרובים
כרחוקים, kerovim ke-rechokim, whether you're a relative or not a relative, פסולים
ככשרים, psulim ke-ksherim, whether you're unfit for testimony or not, וחייב על
כל אחת ואחת בפני בית דין ושלא בפני בית דין, ve-chayav al
kol achat ve-achat bifnei beit din ve-shelo bifnei beit din, and you're
חייב chayav multiple times even in the presence of a court. Right,
remember here you're only חייב chayav multiple times if the שבועה shvuah
was outside the court. And even though you're חייב chayav in that
broad array of cases, אינו מדבר אלא בתביעת ממון, eino medaber ela
bi-tvi'at mamon, it's only monetary. עדות שלא עשה בה נשים כאנשים וקרובים
כרחוקים ופסולים ככשרים, Edut she-lo asah bah nashim ke-anashim u-kerovim ke-rechokim u-psulim
ke-ksherim, but a עדות edut which is much more limited, men, כשר,
kasher, not relative, ואינו חייב אלא אחת בפני בית דין, ve-eino chayav
ela achat bifnei beit din, only one oath in front of court,
אינו דין שלא יהא מדבר אלא בתביעת ממון? eino din she-lo yehei
medaber ela bi-tvi'at mamon? Certainly to have the same limit of only
talking, because it's more limited in general, of only talking about monetary
cases. Okay, we will continue with this tomorrow.